<!DOCTYPE preface SYSTEM "../resources/plainbook/plainbook.dtd" >
<preface id="pre_about" title="About this document">
	<p>This document is a step-by-step guide for Cucumber,
	a tool that is quickly becoming the weapon of choice for many agile teams when it comes to functional test automation, creating
	executable specifications and building a living documentation. We believe in iterative development so we write and publish iteratively.</p>
<section id="pre_about_whatsnew" title="What's new in this version">
  <p>In this version, we have started working on the explaining effective web testing and expanded several sections on gherkin:</p>
  <ul>
  <li><link ref="sec_hooks" /></li>
  <li><link ref="sec_debugging_java" /></li>
  <li><link ref="sec_comparison_tools"/></li>
  <li>a new chapter on organising web automation for easy maintenance (<link ref="chp_three_layers"/>)</li>
  <li>a new chapter on web testing in Ruby with Rails and Sinatra (<link ref="chp_gordons_alive" />)</li>
  <li>and a lot of minor fixes and tweaks</li>
  </ul>
</section>
<section id="pre_about_online" title="Online">
 <p>To get notified when we publish an update, grab the code for the examples we used in the guide, 
	provide feedback or ask a question, do one or more of the following: </p>
	<ul>
	<li>Point your browser to <url link="http://cuke4ninja.com"/> periodically</li>
	<li>Follow @cuke4ninja on Twitter for updates and news</li>
	<li>Follow @davedf and @gojkoadzic on Twitter to keep in touch with the authors or drop us a message there</li>
	</ul> 
</section>
<section id="pre_about_contribuninja" title="Become a contribuninja">
	<p>
		Do you have an interesting story to tell about cucumbers? It is related to the right kind of
		cucumbers? Is it morally acceptable? Do you have a different opinion about any of the things we
		wrote here? Please get engaged and help us make this document better. 
	</p>
	<p>See <url link="http://cuke4ninja.com/contribuninja" />
		for more information on how to contribute.
	</p>
</section>
</preface>
