<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../resources/plainbook/plainbook.dtd" >
<chapter title="Cucumber feature files" id="chp_feature_files">
  <p>In this chapter, we look at the structure of a Cucumber feature file. You will learn:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>The elements of feature files</li>
    <li>How to write some basic scenarios so that Cucumber can understand them</li>
    <li>What makes a good feature file</li>
  </ul>
<section id="sec_cucumber_jargon" title="Cucumber jargon">
        <p>We all know that Ninjas all speak Japanese fluently, but this book is in English. To ensure that nobody gets killed by mistake by
        saying a wrong word, here are some of the basic phrases that you need to memorise:</p>
        <section title="Stakeholder">
            <p>
                A <define>stakeholder</define> is a person who gets some value out of the system. Typical stakeholders are
                representative of groups of users, for example a trader or an administrator. Some teams describe
                stakeholders with user personae
                (explained in <i>User Stories Applied</i><bib ref="cohn:userstory"/>). Personae are particularly useful
                for web-based projects as they encourage you to think about how a typical user is likely to interact with
                the system &ndash; for example, to look at a monitor in despair.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section title="Feature">
            <p>
                A
                <define>feature</define> 
                is a piece of system functionality that delivers value to one or more stakeholders. Executable
                specifications work best when described from the perspective of stakeholders, not software developers,
 since this enables business users to understand them better and engage more in
                discussions about what makes a particular feature complete.
            </p>
            <p>Features are normally vertical
                functional slices of the system, for example credit card processing. Horizontal infrastructural
                slices, for example database caching, are not good as features. They do not deliver value
                directly to any stakeholders. Stakeholders will not be able to engage properly in specifying the
                acceptance
                criteria for such functionality, pretty much defeating the point of specification by example.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section title="User story">
            <p>
                A
                <define>user story</define>
                is a rough description of scope for future work, used as a planning tool. Stories are vertical
                slices of system functionality that are deliverable independently. Each story should specify the
                value it brings to one or more stakeholders, the stakeholders that care about the story
                and the scope of the intended work. A common format for the stories is:
            </p>

            <quote>
                In order to..., As a ..., I want ...
            </quote>
            <p>
                There are alternative formats, such as:
            </p>
            <quote>As a ..., I want..., So that...</quote>
            <p>Many a ninja has died in the futile format wars and some silly shoguns will try to convince you that 
one way of telling stories is significantly better than the other one. Ninja cucumber disagrees! For the purposes of
 this document all the formats are equivalent and we won't enter into a discussion
                on which one is better.
            </p>
            <p>
                Stories often impact several features &ndash; a payment story might have an impact on card
                processing, fraud control and back-office reporting. Stories are often
                relatively small chunks of work, helping developers to deliver new functionality frequently. A single feature might be delivered through a large number of
                stories.
            </p>
            <note title="Stories are more than just the format">
                <p>
                    Many junior ninjas confuse stories with the cards that they are written on. Here is an example of a good user story:
                </p>
                <quote>In order to reduce fraud, as a financial controller I want the system to automatically
                    send Chuck Norris to beat up suspected fraudsters.
                </quote>
                <p>This story clearly states who cares about some functionality, why it is important and what it delivers. This provides
                    enough
                    information for a meaningful discussion on the specifications when the time comes to implement it.
                    Here is
                    an example of a bad user story:
                </p>
                <quote>As a trader I want to enter a trade because I want to trade</quote>
                <p>Although this story obeys the form, it is too broad, too generic and it does not state a clear
                    benefit.
                    It would be much better to specify a full flow of activities that provides
                    some end-to-end value to a stakeholder. We would normally look for thin slices of functionality, for
                    example
                    not supporting all possible trade types or trade workflows from the start but only one type. In this
                    way,
                    once a story is delivered some stakeholders can actually start getting the value from it.
                </p>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section title="Feature file">
            <p>A
                <define>feature file</define>
                describes a feature or a part of a feature with representative examples of expected outcomes. Cucumber
                uses these files to validate some system functionality against its specifications. Feature files are
                plain-text files, ideally stored in the same version control system as the related project.
            </p>
            <p>Here is an example of a Cucumber feature file:</p>
            <code file="ruby/NinjaSurvivalRate/features/ninja_survival_rate.feature"/>
            <p>Later in this chapter we cover how Cucumber interprets this file.</p>
        </section>
        <section title="Key examples">
            <p>
                Each feature should be illustrated with
                <define>key examples</define>. The examples show the expected outcomes in specific representative
                cases with very precise
                information. This makes it absolutely clear what the system is expected to do and helps to avoid
                any misunderstanding and ambiguity. It also makes it possible for an automation tool, such as
                Cucumber, to check whether the system works according to the specification.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section title="Scenario">
            <p>
                A
                <define>scenario</define>
                captures one key example for a feature in the feature file. It represents a way that the system
                delivers some value to a stakeholder. Scenarios are units of specifications for Cucumber. They
                allow us to chop up feature functionality like sushi, into chunks that can be separately consumed. 
                Examples of good scenarios for credit card processing might be successful
                transaction authorisation, transaction failure due to lack of funds, transaction failure due to
                wrong verification code and so on.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section title="Step">
            <p>
                <define>Steps</define>
                are domain language phrases that we can combine to write scenarios. They can refer to the context
                of a scenario, an action that the scenario describes, or a way to validate the action. The steps that
                define the context of a scenario generally begin with the
                <define>Given</define>
                keyword, for example:
                <quote>Given the ninja has a third-level black belt</quote>
             
The steps that define an action generally begin with the
                <define>When</define>
                keyword, for example:
                <quote>When attacked by a samurai</quote>
                The steps that define an expected outcome generally start with the
                <define>Then</define>
                keyword, for example:
                <quote>Then the ninja should engage the opponent</quote>              
            </p>
        </section>
        <section title="Step definitions">
            <p>
                <define>Step definitions</define>
                are reusable automation components that execute individual steps. They tell Cucumber what to do when
                interpreting a particular step (see <link ref="img_cuke_steps"/>). Programmers or automation specialists
                write step definitions where necessary when implementing scenarios to validate that they work correctly.
                Once a step definition is implemented, the step can be reused in other scenarios. We cover how to write
                step definitions in Ruby, .NET and Java in the following chapters.
            </p>
        </section>
        <img src="cuke-steps.png" title="Cucumber step definitions automate validation" id="img_cuke_steps"/>
        <section title="Gherkin">
            <p>
                <define>Gherkin</define>
                is the language for describing Cucumber feature files. It is also the name of a separate piece of
                software that interprets that language.
            </p>
            <p>Gherkin the language defines the structure of a feature
                file and the keywords that can be used to describe features. 
                Gherkin the software parses files for Cucumber and related projects, such as
                Specflow.<footnote>
                    <url link="http://specflow.org"/> is a native .NET implementation
                of a Gherkin-compliant automation tool
                </footnote>
                You can use it to implement your own version
                of Cucumber for a platform that is not currently supported, if you can find one.
            </p>
        </section>
    </section>

<section title="How Cucumber interprets feature files" id="sec_file_interpret">
	<p>
		Let's look into how Cucumber interprets files. Here is the previous
		example again, with italics added to point out the keywords (Cucumber files are normally just
		plain text):
	</p>
<code>
<i>Feature:</i>	Fight or flight
  In order to increase the ninja survival rate,
  As a ninja commander
  I want my ninjas to decide whether to take on an 
  opponent based on their skill levels
 
<i>Scenario:</i> Weaker opponent
    <i>Given</i> the ninja has a third level black-belt 
    <i>When</i> attacked by a samurai
    <i>Then</i> the ninja should engage the opponent

 
<i>Scenario:</i> Stronger opponent
    <i>Given</i> the ninja has a third level black-belt 
    <i>When </i> attacked by Chuck Norris
    <i>Then </i> the ninja should run for his life 
</code>
	    <p>Each feature file starts with the
			<code>Feature</code> keyword (if in English, we'll deal with other languages later). The keyword is followed by a colon and the feature title. In this case, the feature title is: 
			    <quote>Fight or flight</quote>
			The title of a feature should help a reader understand what the file is about. 
			<note>
			A good technique for deciding on
			a title is to think about what you would type into Google to search for this file if it were online.
			</note>
			</p>
			<p>
				The paragraph that follows the feature title is free-form text that describes the 
				purpose of the feature. In this case, the feature description is:
				<quote> In order to increase the ninja survival rate, as a ninja commander I want my ninjas to
					decide whether to take on an opponent based on their skill levels</quote>
This paragraph should provide the context to enable the reader to understand the rest of
				the file. 
			To describe a feature, name the stakeholder, the benefit and
				the intended solution. 	
</p>
<p>
Describing features in the user-story format is a common practice, although they do not
				necessarily map directly onto user stories. A description in the user-story format also helps people decide later whether a new scenario
				belongs to a particular feature file or not. 
			<note>
			A good strategy for describing a feature is to
				write the scenarios first, then summarise them and explain them to someone who hasn't seen them before.
				Capture the explanation you used and put it into the Feature paragraph the file. This will ensure that the
				feature file is self-explanatory.
			</note>
			</p>
			<p>
				One or more scenarios follow the introductory paragraph, each starting with the
				<code>Scenario</code>
				keyword, followed by a colon and a scenario title on the first line. In this example, the
				scenarios are:
				<quote>Weaker opponent</quote>
				and
				<quote>Stronger opponent</quote>
				The title of a scenario should provide the context to enable the reader to understand the key example described by
				the scenario. A good strategy to use when deciding on a scenario title is to try to summarise the purpose of
				an example covered by the scenario to another person, and capture the phrase you used to explain
				it.
			</p>
			<p>
				Each scenario is described with one or more steps. In this example, the steps of the second
				scenario are:<quote><p>Given the ninja has a third-level black belt</p> 
				    <p>When attacked by Chuck Norris</p>
				    <p>Then the ninja should run for his life</p>
			    </quote>
		    </p>
	<note title="Feature files are your katanas">
		<p>Ninja always knows where his katana is. You should know the same for your feature files. 
		      They form living documentation for a software system. They allow developers to
			understand what needs to be implemented, testers to understand what is being automatically
			checked and business users and support staff to quickly discover exactly what the system does.
			They are not just test scripts. Feature files should be kept safe and secure as much as the
			system code. When the code is branched, tagged or merged, these specifications should follow. The
			easiest way to do this is to keep them in the same version control system as the code.</p>
	</note>
    </section>
    <section id="sec_good_feature_file" title="What makes a good feature file">
	<p>
		The long term benefit of using Cucumber comes from living documentation, a source of information
		on system functionality that is easily accessible to everyone and always current. To achieve that,
		a feature file should be:
	</p>
	    <ul>
		    <li>Easy to understand</li>
		    <li>Consistent</li>
		    <li>Easy to access</li>
	    </ul>
		<p>To serve as a target for development that prevents misunderstanding and ambiguity, scenarios
		in a feature file should be:</p>   
	    <ul>    
		    <li>Precise and testable</li>
		    <li>Specifications, not scripts</li>
		    <li>About business functionality, not about software design</li>
	    </ul>
	    <p>Once a feature is implemented, the related file becomes a living document for the feature. 
	    To allow the software to evolve and provide functional regression checks, the scenarios should be:</p>
	    <ul>
		    <li>Self-explanatory</li>
		    <li>Focused</li>
		    <li>In domain language</li>
	    </ul>
		<p>Write your feature files as if they will be read by an angry Chuck Norris looking for an excuse to beat you up
		if they are hard to understand. Think about them as documentation that will be read much more than it
		will be changed. Consider that other people will need to read and understand it months or years
		after you write it. Here are some things to watch out for:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Very long files or scenarios: these are hard to understand, so break them apart or try to
				describe the feature from a higher level of abstraction</li>
			<li>Technical automation concepts: these belong in step definitions (code), not scenarios
				(human-readable text). Mixing the two makes the scenarios harder to understand and change.</li>
			<li>Generic values in examples: For example &lsquo;Given a card with a valid number&rsquo; where
				valid is not precisely defined somewhere else, or &lsquo;Then the system should work
				correctly&rsquo;. Generic values can be ambiguous and cause misunderstanding. Examples should be
				realistic and very precise. Use an example of a valid number (and specify another scenario that
				illustrates an invalid number). Define what &lsquo;correctly&rsquo; means by illustrating it with
				the precise output.</li>
			<li>Inconsistent language: As the project evolves, the domain language might change. Cucumber
				feature files are your documentation, update them to be consistent with the updated language or people
				won't be able to understand them later.</li>
			<li>Several actions or mixed validations and actions: although a scenario that checks several
				cases makes a perfectly good regression check, it is really hard to understand. Each scenario
				should be independent, focused on a single example and perform a single action. That will make them
				easier to understand later. It also enables developers and testers to get quick
				feedback from individual checks.</li>
			<li>Generic feature explanations or titles of features and scenarios that do not explain the
				content of the file completely. Feature files should be self-explanatory. A good litmus test for
				this is to show the feature file to someone who hasn't seen it and ask them to explain it back to
				you. If their understanding of it differs from yours, then the descriptions are wrong.</li>
		</ul>
    </section>	
	<section id="sec_collaborative_feature_files" title="Feature files should be written collaboratively">
		<p>Many beginners fail with specification by example by expecting the business analysts or business users
		to write feature files on their own. You can see people often complaining how Cucumber doesn't work for them because
		their business analysts don't want to write feature files. This is a huge misunderstanding of the process
		and you should avoid having them write the files on their own, even if they are willing. Feature files should be 
		a universally accepted definition of what makes a particular story complete, from all the perspectives.		
		That is why they need to be specified and written collaboratively. Everyone should contribute. 
		A good feature file contains the following key examples:
		</p>
			<ul>
				<li>A representative example illustrating each important aspect of business functionality. Business
					users, analysts or customers will typically define these.</li>
				<li>An example illustrating each important technical edge case, such as
					technical boundary conditions.
					Developers will typically suggest such examples when they are concerned about functional gaps
					or inconsistencies. Business users, analysts or customers will
					define the correct expected behaviour.</li>
				<li>An example illustrating each particularly troublesome area of the expected implementation,					
					such as cases that caused bugs in the past and boundary conditions that might not be explicitly
					illustrated by previous examples. Testers will typically suggest these and business
					users, analysts or customers will define the correct behaviour.</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
        <section id="sec_structuring_scenarios" title="Structuring scenarios">
		<p>
			Although there is no syntax check to prevent misuse, the steps in a scenario should follow the
			<define>Given-When-Then</define>
			flow, which means that the preconditions come first, then an action, and then the expected
			outcome of the action. Structuring scenarios like this ensures that they are focused and makes them
			easier to understand.
		</p>
		<section title="Given">
			<p>
				A
				<code>Given</code>
				step defines the preconditions for a scenario, such as Chunk Norris showing up being a precondition for a good fight. Technically, the step definition that automates it
				should put the system into a known state for an automated test.
			</p>
			<p>
				<code>Given</code>
				steps should describe the state of the world before an interesting action. Avoid writing them as
				actions, but instead explain the state. For example, it is much better to write:
			</p>
			<code>Given a ninja is in the room</code>
			<p>than</p>
			<code>Given a ninja enters a room</code>
			<p> This distinction might not seem so important initially, but it helps to focus
				readers' attention on the important action in the scenario and avoid falling into the
				trap of scripting.</p>
		</section>
		<section title="When">
			<p>
				A
				<code>When</code>
				step describes the primary action of a scenario &ndash;
in the case of Chuck Norris almost guaranteed to involve some kicking. Some good examples of the primary action are:
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>An activity of a user</li>
				<li>A domain event</li>
				<li>A system function</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				Try to write
				<code>When</code> steps
				as actions, something that happens. This will focus the attention of the reader on the actions. It will
				also help developers understand where to put the business logic and how to call the appropriate code
				modules to implement the functionality.
			</p>
		</section>
	<section title="Then">
		<p>
			A
			<code>Then</code>
			step specifies tears, black eyes and such. They are post-conditions, expected observable outcomes of the primary action in the given
			context. It is important that these are observable outcomes, something that the business users can
			actually understand and see. Otherwise, they won't be able to engage in specifying it.
			Internal state changes, though they may be easy to test, do not guarantee that the user of the
			system benefits in any way from the feature.
		</p>
		<important title="But I want to verify internal changes">
			<p>Verifying internal changes might be very important from a technical perspective, but the
				business users often couldn't care less about it. Use a technical tool (such as your
				favourite unit testing tool) to specify and verify such things. You'll get a much faster
				turnround from a technical perspective. You don't really need a test that is readable and
				accessible by business users for these kinds of checks, so using Cucumber for them won't give you any real
 benefits.</p>
		</important>
	</section>
	<p>You can use three double-quote symbols (<code>"""</code>) to start and end a multi-line block. For example:
	<code>
	Given a ninja has the following hit-list """
		5 Samurai
		10 Peasants
		1 Shogun
		0 Chucks
	"""
	</code>
	</p>
	
<section id="sec_difference_when_then" title="The difference between When and Then">
	<p>
		Spoken languages have quite a lot of ambiguity and flexibility. The same thing can be said in lots
		of different ways, which often confuses people when they start with Gherkin. For example, we can
		say:
		<quote>Given the opponent is Chuck Norris, then the ninja should run for his life</quote>
		Using
		<code>When</code>
		instead of
		<code>Given</code>
		doesn't change the meaning at all:
		<quote>When the opponent is Chuck Norris, then the ninja should run for his life</quote>
	</p>
	<note title="Syntax error in the previous example">
	<p>
		Those among you
		who read this carefully will surely know that it is a syntax error to use Chuck Norris in a
		<code>Given</code>
		step, as he does not take orders from anyone. The current version of Cucumber has a bug and does
		not report this as a syntax error but this will probably be fixed in the future.
	</p>
	</note>
	<p>
	In Gherkin, however, there is a huge difference.
	<code>Given</code>
	steps describe the world as it is before an action happens, and
	<code>When</code>
	describes the action that is played out in a scenario. Think of it this way: each scenario explains
	an action. A context for the action (<code>Given</code>) is optional, but the action (<code>When</code>) is mandatory.
</p>	
</section>
</section>

<section id="sec_internationalisation" title="Internationalisation">
	<p>One of the biggest advantages of Cucumber over other literal automation tools is that it fully supports
	 internationalisation. You do not have to use keywords in English. You can write the feature file in around 40
	  languages, including some very obscure such as LOLCATS and artificial languages such as Welsh.
          Here is, for example, the feature file from the introduction in French:</p>		
		<code>
Fonctionnalit&eacute;: Lutte ou de fuite
    Afin d'augmenter le taux de survie ninja,
    Tant que commandant ninja
    Je veux que mon ninjas de d&eacute;cider de prendre un adversaire 
      en fonction de leurs niveaux de comp&eacute;tences

Plan du Sc&eacute;nario: ennemi plus faible
    Soit le Ninja a un troisi&egrave;me niveau ceinture noire
    Lorsqu'il est attaqu&eacute; par un samoura&iuml;
    Alors le ninja doit engager l'adversaire

Plan du Sc&eacute;nario: ennemi plus fort
    Soit le Ninja a un troisi&egrave;me niveau ceinture noire
    Lorsqu'il est attaqu&eacute; par Jean-Claude Van Damme
    Alors le ninja doit fuir pour sauver sa vie
		</code>
		<p>See the 
		<url title="Cucumber wiki examples" link="http://github.com/aslakhellesoy/cucumber/blob/master/examples/i18n" /> for 
		more examples in all the supported languages.</p>
</section>
       

<section id="sec_gherkin_tag" title="Tagging for fun and profit">
<p>After a few months, scenarios and features in a project can become unwieldy. With hundreds of feature files, we might 
not want to run everything all the time. It is often useful to be able to quickly find or check just a subset of the 
features, for 
example in order to omit one or two very slow tests to get faster feedback. </p>
<p>Cucumber allows us to manage large groups of scenarios more easily with tags. Tags are free-form text comments assigned to a scenario. They
provide meta-data about the type, nature or group of that scenario. You can assign a tag to a scenario by putting it before the scenario header, adding
an &lsquo;at&rsquo; sign (@) before the tag name. For example:</p>
<code>
 @slowtest
 Scenario: end-to-end signup
 ...
</code>
<p>You can execute only the scenarios with a particular tag using the <code>--tags</code> option, for example:</p>
<code>cucumber --tags @fasttest</code>
<p>Another option is to skip the scenarios with a particular tag. For this, prefix the tag with a tilde (~). Here is an example:</p>
<code>cucumber --tags ~@slowtest</code>
<p>Here are some useful things you can do with tags:</p>
<ul>
<li>Identify work-in-progress to avoid breaking the build when newly introduced scenarios fail.</li>
<li>Separate quick and slow checks and execute as cascaded builds on the build server to speed up feedback.</li>
<li>Execute some checks overnight only.</li>
<li>Cross-reference stories and features or scenarios.</li>
<li>Link entire feature areas and scenarios that have cross-cutting issues.</li>
</ul>

<p>You can tag a feature or a scenario. Feature tags are automatically inherited by all the enclosed scenarios and scenario outlines. Cucumber
also supports some more advanced tag features, such as enforcing the limit on the number of scenarios with a particular tag (useful for work-in-progress) and
running scenarios that satisfy a combination of tags. For information on those options, have a look at 
the <url link="https://github.com/cucumber/cucumber/wiki/tags" title="tags page on the Cucumber wiki"/>.</p>
</section>
<section title="Remember">
<ul>
<li>Describe features from the perspectives of users and stakeholders, not software developers</li>
<li>Think of feature files as documentation when you write them.</li>
<li>Define the examples for feature files collaboratively.</li>
<li>Given steps describe the world as it was before an action. When steps describe activities that cause the world to change. Then steps specify how the world shuld change.</li> 
</ul>
</section>
</chapter>
