<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../resources/plainbook/plainbook.dtd" >
<chapter title="Cucumber and Ruby" id="chp_hello_ruby">
    <p>
        In this chapter, we cover setting up Cucumber for a Ruby project.
    </p>
    <sidebar title="Do you have Ruby installed?">
        <p>
            In this chapter, we assume you have already installed ruby on your system. If this is not the case, there is
            more information on the <url link="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/" title="Ruby site"/>.
        </p>
        <p>
            If you are running Windows
            there are some notes on installing Ruby in <link ref="chp_hello_dotnet"/>
        </p>
    </sidebar>
    <section id="sec_ruby_install_cucumber" title="Installing Cucumber">
    <p>To automate feature files using Ruby you need to install the <code>cucumber</code> gem.
            Do that with the following command:
        </p>
        <code>gem install cucumber</code>
        <p>Check that Cucumber is installed by running the following command in the terminal window:</p>
        <code>cucumber --version</code>
        <p>Cucumber should print out the version (0.9.0 at the time when we wrote this). </p>
        <p>Cucumber uses
         RSpec for assertions. If you do not already have
            RSpec, run the following command to install it:
        </p>
        <code>gem install rspec</code>
        <important title="Cucumber won't install!">
        <p>
            Cucumber depends on a particular gherkin version. It will try to download it automatically, but
            if you already have a later version then RubyGems gets confused and won't download the version
            required by Cucumber. As a result you might get an error message similar to this one:
        </p>
        <code>ERROR:  Error installing cucumber:
        cucumber requires gherkin (~> 2.2.2, runtime)</code>
        <p>
            To resolve this, install the correct gherkin gem version first:
        </p>
        <code>gem install gherkin --version 2.2.3 </code>
        <p> Or just uninstall the previous version of gherkin if you do not need it for other reasons, and then install the latest version:</p>
        <code>
        gem uninstall gherkin
        gem install gherkin        
        </code>
        </important>
	</section>
    <section title="Hello World from Ruby" id="sec_ruby_hello_world">
        <p>Let's go through a quick sample project to verify that the installation works.
                Create a directory for the project, for example <code>HelloCucumber</code>.
                Create a <code>features</code> directory in it. This is where the feature files go.
                Create a new file in it, called <code>basic.feature</code>, with the following content:
            </p>
            <code file="ruby/HelloCucumber/features/basic.feature"/>
            <p>Run <code>cucumber</code> from the command line in the main project directory.
            When it cannot match steps to step definitions, Cucumber prints out what it thinks
            would be a good default setup for the steps. As we have not implemented any steps yet,
            Cucumber
            should print a suggestion similar to the one in <link ref="fig.ruby_suggestions" />.
          	</p>
            <p>
                Now create a sub-directory called <code>step_definitions</code> in the <code>features</code> directory. This
                is where the automation layer between the feature files and the domain code goes. Create a new file
                called <code>basic_steps.rb</code> in the <code>step_definitions</code> directory. You project structure should end up looking something like in <link ref="fig_ruby_project_structure" />.
                 Paste the following content into <code>basic_steps.rb</code>:
            </p>
            <code file="ruby/HelloCucumber/features/step_definitions/basic_steps.rb"/>
          	<img src="ruby_suggestions.png" id="fig.ruby_suggestions" title="Cucumber suggests a default implementation for step definitions"/>
            <p>
                This is a very simplistic implementation for all the steps, that does not actually
                connect to any domain code. We go through all the details of the feature file and step definitions in <link ref="chp_feature_files" />. For now,
                you can probably guess that Cucumber uses regular expression after the keywords <code>Given</code>, <code>When</code> and <code>Then</code>
                to map lines in a feature file to step definitions.
            </p>
            <img id="fig_ruby_project_structure" src="ruby_project_structure.png" title="Ruby project folders"/>
            <p>
                Now we are ready to run the features. Run

            <code>cucumber</code> again from the command line in your main project directory, and you should
            get a result similar to the one in <link ref="fig_ruby_test_results" />.  This tells us the number of
             features and steps executed, the lines of the step definitions, the steps
                executed and reports successful and failed test executions.</p>
	    <img id="fig_ruby_test_results" title="Our feature works in Ruby" src="ruby_test_results.png"/>
    </section>
</chapter>
