<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../resources/plainbook/plainbook.dtd" >
<chapter title="Why should you care about Cucumber?" id="chp_introduction">
    <p>
        Ninja is one of the most popular types of cucumbers in Thailand and South-Eastern Asia.
        Ninja plants start to set fruits 35 days after sowing and continue to produce cucumbers for a long time,
        making Ninjas excellent for both home gardens and commercial growing.<footnote>
            <url link="http://www.evergreenseeds.com/orcuhyni.html"/>
        </footnote>
    </p>
    <p>Oh, no... sorry about that, wrong type of cucumber. Let's try again.</p>
    <p>Cucumber is a functional test automation tool for lean and agile teams. It supports behaviour-driven
        development, specification by example and agile acceptance testing. You can use it to
        automate functional validation in a form that is easily readable and understandable to business users,
        developers and testers. This helps teams create <i>executable specifications</i>,
        that are a goal for development, acceptance criteria and functional regression checks for future changes. 
        In this way, Cucumber allows teams to create <i>living documentation</i>, a single authoritative source of
        information on system functionality that is always up-to-date.
    </p>
    <note title="Executable what?">
        <p>
            Yes, executable specifications. You can use Cucumber to execute checks based on your
            specifications against the software automatically, when you use specification by example. To keep
            this document short we won't go into specification by example, how behaviour-driven development
            works or how best to apply agile acceptance testing. There are some nice references in
            <link ref="app_resources"/>
            for further research.
        </p>
    </note>
    <p>Cucumber is quickly becoming as popular with teams that develop and maintain web-based systems as the shuriken
        is with <url link="http://www.crazyapplerumors.com/?p=1273" title="Steve Jobs"/>. Teams love Cucumber because of its
        flexibility and support for web automation frameworks. It started as a tool for Ruby, but now supports a wide
        variety of platforms. This makes it appealing to teams that work with JVM-based languages and even those shinobi
        that use the dark magic of .NET.
    </p>
    <section id="sec_why_cucumber" title="Why use Cucumber?">
        <p>
            Cucumber is one of the rare tools that try very hard to stay out of your way, to let you do your work
            without making you worry about the tool itself too much. It helps teams automate their specifications
            efficiently in several ways:
        </p>

        <ul>
            <li>It is relatively easy to set up.</li>
            <li>It supports multiple report formats, including HTML and PDF.</li>
            <li>It supports writing specifications in about 40 spoken languages, making it easy for teams outside of
                English-speaking territories or those working on internationally targeted software to engage their
                business users better.
            </li>
            <li>It supports different ways of describing executable specifications &mdash; including story-like prose,
                lists and tabular data. You can unleash your inner writer, or more likely an inner accountant. 
            </li>
            <li>It allows scripting, abstraction and component reuse on several levels, allowing both technical and
                non-technical
                users to efficiently describe specifications and tests.
            </li>
            <li>It generates the tricky parts of the code so that you don't have to write most of the boiler-plate
                automation or make mistakes doing it.
            </li>
            <li>It integrates nicely with the rest of the development ecosystem. It does not try to impose a version
                control system, but works off plain-text files that can be stored in any version control system. For
                continuous build integration, it emulates JUnit. JUnit XML format is, of course, the equivalent of Star Trek transporters when it comes to testing &mdash; use it and you can beam your test results anywhere.
            </li>
            <li>Although Cucumber is a Ruby tool, people who work on other platforms do not have to learn Ruby to use it. You
                can use Cucumber with .NET or JVM languages almost natively.
            </li>
            <li>It's integrated with all the most popular web testing libraries.</li>
            <li>It allows you to cross reference and index tests using tags, so that you can quickly find all tests related to a function or run a group of related tests (eg quick
                tests, slow tests, integration tests, accounting tests).
            </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
            Although you can automate almost anything with it,<footnote>See the Getting Started section of
                <url link="http://wiki.github.com/aslakhellesoy/cucumber/"/>
                for an impressive list of platforms and tools Cucumber integrates with
            </footnote> the killer feature of Cucumber is the ease of web workflow testing.
        </p>
    </section>
    <section id="sec_comparison_tools" title="How does Cucumber compare to other tools?">
	<p>Cucumber is like that brave Athenian soldier who centuries ago decided to test the resilience of humans by running from the Marathon field. It is essentially a test runner. It does a pretty good job of executing automated tests and spitting out reports in lots of various formats,
	    including HTML, PDF, JUnit (for integration with continuous build tools) and colour text on the
	    screen. On the other hand, it doesn't try to do anything before test
	    execution in the process. So there is no Cucumber-IDE or anything
	    similar. There are some external programs for that, mostly of beta
	    quality and in development:</p>
   	<ul>
	    <li><url link="http://github.com/henritersteeg/cuke4vs" /> does syntax highlighting
	    and intellisense in Visual Studio.</li>
    	    <li><url link="http://github.com/QuBiT/cucumber-eclipse-plugin" /> is a plugin for Eclipse</li>
	    <li><url link="http://github.com/cs3b/cucumber_fm/" /> is a website system for
	    Cucumber file management</li>
    	    <li><url link="http://relishapp.com/" /> is a web product in development to
	    publish Cucumber files as a nice web site</li>
    	    <li><url link="http://21croissants.github.com/courgette/" /> another web product in
	    development to show files as web pages</li>
	    <li><url link="https://github.com/asterite/cukecooker/" /> is a web based IDE for Cucumber feature files when working in Ruby</li>
	</ul>
	<p> Cucumber files (explained later in this chapter) are plain-text which makes it very simple to edit them but does not allow any clever formatting.  
You can put a short description in a file header, but apart from that everything else in the file is related to scenarios and test cases. That means that there is no way to include images, hyperlinks, rich-text descriptions and similar.
	</p>
	<p>Cucumber's step
	    definition (automation layer, integration to domain API, explained in later chapters) model is very simple, which is 
	    both a strength
	    and a weakness in different contexts. A simple API makes it very easy
	    to understand and learn what you can do with Cucumber, so you won't
	    spend three months getting your head around all the possible ways to
	    use tables. On the other hand, it doesn't have the smart domain-object
	    mapping features that some other tools have, which allow you to expose your domain
	    objects and services directly for testing and provide lots of
	    flexibility in how you can manage complex scenarios.
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section id="sec_cucumber_bdd" title="What does Cucumber have to do with BDD">
        <p>Aspiring Cucumber  ninjas are well advised that Cucumber is frequently mentioned in the context of Behaviour driven Development (BDD). In fact, Cucumber is as closely tied to BDD as Chuck Norris is to his beard. Dan North, the central authority on BDD, summarised BDD as:<footnote>
            See
            <url link="http://skillsmatter.com/podcast/java-jee/how-to-sell-bdd-to-the-business" />
        </footnote>
           </p>
        <quote>A second generation, outside-in, pull based, multiple stakeholder,
            multiple scale, high automation, agile methodology
        </quote>
           <section title="Second Generation">
           <p>BDD came out of merging ideas of Extreme Programming, Lean software development and Domain Driven Design,
            as a second-generation agile process that helps teams deliver high quality software and answers many of the
            most confusing questions of early agile processes, such as the ones dealing with documentation and testing.
        </p>
       </section>
           <section title="Outside-in and pull-based">
           <p>BDD takes the ideas of value chains and pulling features from Lean manufacturing, ensuring that the right software
               is built by focusing on the expected outputs of the system and ensuring that these outputs are achieved.
               Teams achieve this by collaborating on specifications and illustrating the specifications with key examples
               of expected outcomes. These specifications are created just in time when they are needed, from user stories
               and use cases that get pulled into development.</p>
       </section>
       <section title="Multiple-stakeholder">
           <p>BDD dispenses with the idea that there is a single amorphous &lsquo;user&rsquo; of the system, and recognises that
               different groups of people will be affected with the software in different ways. In Quality Software Management, Gerald Weinberg wrote that &lsquo;Quality is value to some person&rsquo;.
               BDD forces the delivery teams
               to understand and define quality, by specifying <i>who</i> are the people that the software will bring some value to and <i>what</i> will be valuable to them. </p>
       </section>
       <section title="Multiple-scale">
           <p>A core idea of BDD is to clearly specify the expected outputs with realistic examples and then develop the software to achieve those outputs. This works on multiple levels. On the top level, we can work with high-level examples of how a feature will be useful in a holistic way. Below that, we can look at the impact of that on individual functional areas of the system. Below that we can work on technical implementation units. The process is the same, regardless of the level. </p>
       </section>
       <section title="Agile">
           <p>BDD works best with short iterations or flow-based work, where teams specify, implement and deliver relatively small
               chunks of functionality. It requires cross-functional teams to collaborate on specifications and tests.</p>
       </section>
       <section title="High-automation">
           <p>Once the expected quality is defined, the team will need to check the system functionality frequently and compare it to the expected results. To make this check efficient, it has to be automated. BDD relies heavily on automation of executable
               specifications. </p>
               <p>Cucumber takes care of the &lsquo;high-automation&rsquo; part of the BDD definition. It allows teams to describe features in a business language, with key examples, and automate the validation of those features against system functionality.</p>
       </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
