<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../resources/plainbook/plainbook.dtd" >
<chapter title="Cucumber and The Three Layers of UI Automation" id="chp_three_layers">
	<note title="Work in progress">
		<p>This chapter is still being written! Nothing to see here... move along</p>
	</note>
	<section title="Why three layers?">
		<p>
			Many ninja children are told the story of Cucumber and the three layers of UI Automation, in which the the
			abstract concept of layers of responsibility are represented by bears who are too weak to eat hot porridge
			and the little ninja comes in and eats the porridge and totally flips out, absolutely killing everyone in the story and
			other nearby stories. Ahh the carnage is truly a sight to behold...
		</p>
		<p>Sorry, ignore that last bit.</p>
		<p>
			There are a number of tools available for automating UI testing. Some of these tools use the dark magic of the Geisha to
			seduce young ninjas int believing that they can build up a suite of tests by recording actions performed on
			the site to produce automation scripts. These scripts will then form the basis of an ongoing UI automation suite
		</p>
		<p>
			At first, all seems to go well. Scripts are quickly recorded and the tests all pass. Adding more tests is easy.
			After a few months, new features are added however, which change a number of core pages of the site. Suddenly 
			all the tests are broken! The ninjas are starting to realise that they have been tricked by the Geisha magic. 
			Their anger turns to despair, however, once they look at the scripts produced in the first stage of their journey.
			It is written in a strange language from a far off land, and used twelve words where the ninjas would usually use one.
			The ninjas realise that the test scripts are completely unmaintainable, and must be thrown away. They are the victims of the 
			Mount Fuji of death spell (also known as the sine wave of death)<footnote><url link="http://gojko.net/2010/07/29/the-sine-of-death-by-ui-test-automation/"></url></footnote>
		</p>
	</section>
</chapter>